<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="flexaddon">
    <title>Working with the Flex Addon for Spring Roo</title>
    <sect1 id="flexaddon-introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            Spring Roo brings brings a whole new level of productivity to building Java applications.  From the Spring Roo Reference Guide:
        </para>
        <para>
            "<ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/roo">Spring Roo</ulink> is an easy-to-use productivity tool for rapidly building enterprise applications in the 
            Java programming language. It allows you to build high-quality, high-performance, lock-in-free enterprise applications in just minutes. Best of all, Roo 
            works alongside your existing Java knowledge, skills and experience. You probably won't need to learn anything new to use Roo, as there's no new language 
            or runtime platform needed. You simply program in your normal Java way and Roo just works, sitting in the background taking care of the things you don't 
            want to worry about."
        </para>
        <para>
            To learn more about Spring Roo itself, you'll find numerous resources from the project's homepage at <ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/roo">http://www.springsource.org/roo</ulink>
        </para>
        <para>
            The Flex Addon for Spring Roo aims to raise the bar for developer productivity in building Spring-based RIAs with a Flex client by meeting the 
            following goals:  
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                Provide the fastest way to get a Spring project configured to use Spring BlazeDS Integration set up and running.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Eliminate the need to manually perform repetitive tasks such as keeping ActionScript and Java domain objects in sync.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Automate round-tripping code-generation of Flex artifacts with a focus on letting developers do what they do best - write code.
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <sect2 id="flex-addon-requirements">
            <title>Minimum Requirements for the Flex Addon for Spring Roo</title>
            <para>
                Java 5+
            </para>
            <para>
                Maven 2.2.0+
            </para>
            <para>
                Spring Roo 1.1.0.M1
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="flex-addon-setup">
            <title>Installing the Flex Addon for Spring Roo</title>
            <para>
                The currently released version of the Flex Addon for Spring Roo is 1.0.0.M1.  The addon was included in the Spring BlazeDS Integration 1.5.0.M1 distribution 
                and is also available from the Spring Milestones Maven Repository at <code>http://maven.springframework.org/milestone</code> under the group id 
                <code>org.springframework.flex.roo.addon</code> and artifact id <code>org.springframework.flex.roo.addon</code>.  
                <note><para>The addon is currently under heavy development and an updated 1.0.0.M2 release should be available in the near future.  
                This next release will be available via Addon Discovery feature of Spring Roo 1.1+.  1.5.0.M1 is known to be incompatible with Roo 1.1 and above.  See the 
                Spring Flex community support forums if you are interested in following along with development and trying out the nightly snapshot builds.</para></note>
                
            </para>
            <para>
                First, ensure that you have Spring Roo 1.1.0.M1 set up correctly by following the <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring-roo/reference/html-single/index.html#intro-installation">steps found here</ulink>.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you've not already done so, download the Spring BlazeDS Integration 1.5.0.M1 <ulink url="http://www.springsource.com/download/community?project=Spring%20BlazeDS%20Integration">project distribution</ulink>.
            </para>
            <para>
                Once you have a working Spring Roo installation, you can install the Flex Addon by simply copying it from <code>{spring_blazeds_dist}/org.springframework.flex.roo.addon-1.0.0.M1.jar</code> into the 
                <code>$ROO_HOME/bundle</code> directory.
            </para>
            <para>
                To verify that the Flex Addon has been picked up and activated, start Spring Roo from a clean directory and execute the command <code>osgi scr list</code>.  You should see <code>org.springframework.flex.roo.addon.FlexCommands</code> 
                listed with a status of <code>active</code>.
            </para> 
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="flex-addon-features">
            <title>Flex Addon for Spring Roo Features</title>
            <para>The Flex Addon for Spring Roo provides the following high-level features:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Automated setup of the necessary Spring, Maven, and Eclipse configuration for a standard Spring BlazeDS Integration project.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Generation of Spring BlazeDS Integration <code>@RemotingDestination</code> services with full CRUD capabilities for a given entity.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Continuous synchronization of changes between ActionScript and Java domain classes for AMF remoting.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Generation of UI scaffold that is continuously updated as changes occur in the corresponding ActionScript or Java classes.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Client-side Flex validator generation corresponding to the Bean Validation annotations on the Java model.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="flex-addon-commands">
            <title>Flex Commands</title>
            <para>
                The Flex Addon provides its functionality through just a few simple commands.
            </para>
            <sect3 id="flex-setup-command">
                <title>flex setup</title>
                <para>
                    Once a basic Spring Roo project has been set up, the Flex Addon provides a single <code>flex setup</code> command for adding the necessary Spring, Maven, and Eclipse 
                    configuration for a Flex project backed by Spring BlazeDS Integration.  Its execution is as simple as:  
                </para>
                <programlisting>
org.example.rootunes roo> <emphasis role="bold">flex setup</emphasis>
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/flex
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/flex/services-config.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/spring
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/spring/flex-config.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/spring/webmvc-config.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/web.xml
Created SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/urlrewrite.xml
Managed SRC_MAIN_WEBAPP/WEB-INF/web.xml
...
                </programlisting>
                <para>
                    Once you have the basic Flex project infrastructure in place, you can start generating remoting destinations and scaffolding.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="flex-remoting-scaffold-command">
                <title>flex remoting scaffold</title>
                <para>
                    The <code>flex remoting scaffold</code> command will create a Spring-managed <code>@RemotingDestination</code> and Flex UI scaffolding for a given Java domain entity.  It 
                    requires a <code>--name</code> option that specifies the name of the <code>@RemotingDestination</code> class to be created, and an <code>--entity</code> option which will 
                    be inferred from the current Roo command context if not specified explicitly. 
                </para>
                <programlisting>
~.domain.Artist roo> <emphasis role="bold">flex remoting scaffold</emphasis> --name ~.service.ArtistService          
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service/ArtistService.java
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/domain
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/domain/Artist.as
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service/ArtistService_Roo_Service.aj
Managed ROOT/src/main/flex/rootunes_scaffold.mxml
Managed ROOT/src/main/flex/rootunes_scaffold-config.xml
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist/ArtistEvent.as
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist/ArtistView.mxml
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist/ArtistForm.mxml 
                </programlisting>
                <para>
                    As shown in the listing above, the command causes the following to be generated:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A <code>@RemotingDestination</code> that provides persistence operations for the given entity.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>An ActionScript class that mirrors the Java entity.  If there were any JPA relationships in the Java entity, additional ActionScript classes would be generated 
                        accordingly.  Once this link is established between an ActionScript and Java class, the addon will automatically keep the two in sync and propagate any changes made to 
                        the fields in either the ActionScript or Java class, whether those changes are made manually in the code, or with the aid of a Roo command.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Flex UI scaffolding for carrying out CRUD operation on the entity.  Anytime fields are added to the ActionScript class, the necessary updates will be made to 
                        the proper .mxml artifacts to reflect the new fields.  (Note - At this time, the Flex addon will not delete fields from the .mxml once they've been added.  The syncronization 
                        capabilities will be expanded in further releases.)
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    The <code>@RemotingDestination</code> that gets generated (in this example, <code>org.example.rootunes.ArtistService</code>), will automatically provide basic CRUD 
                    functionality for the given <code>Artist</code> entity.  The generated methods that provide this functionality are as follows:
                </para>
                <informaltable>
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry align="center">Method Signature </entry>
                                <entry align="center">Comment </entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                              <entry>public Artist <emphasis role="bold">create</emphasis>(Artist artist){..}</entry>
                              <entry>The create method will persist a newly created Artist instance and return the persistent instance.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                              <entry>public Artist <emphasis role="bold">show</emphasis>(Long id) {..}</entry>
                              <entry>The show method will return an existing Artist instance matching the provided id.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                              <entry>public List&lt;Artist&gt; <emphasis role="bold">list</emphasis>() {..}</entry>
                              <entry>The list method will return a list of all existing Artist instances.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                              <entry>public List&lt;Artist&gt; <emphasis role="bold">listPaged</emphasis>(Integer page, Integer size) {..}</entry>
                              <entry>The listPaged method will return a list containing a subset of existing Artist instances according to the provided page and size parameters.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                              <entry>public Artist <emphasis role="bold">update</emphasis>(Artist artist){..}</entry>
                              <entry>The update method will update and already persistent Artist instance and return the persistent instance.</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                              <entry>public void <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis>(Long id){..}</entry>
                              <entry>The delete method will remove an existing Artist instance matching the provided id.</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>                       
                
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="flex-remoting-all-command">
                <title>flex remoting all</title>
                <para>
                    The <code>flex remoting all</code> command is a convenient variation of <code>flex remoting scaffold</code> that will create a Spring-managed <code>@RemotingDestination</code> 
                    and Flex UI scaffolding for all Java domain entities in a given <code>--package</code> if it does not already exist.  Its usage is shown below:
                </para>
                <programlisting>
roo> <emphasis role="bold">flex remoting all</emphasis> --package ~.service
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service/ArtistService.java
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/domain
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/domain/Artist.as
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/domain/Album.as
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service/AlbumService.java
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service/ArtistService_Roo_Service.aj
Managed ROOT/src/main/flex/rootunes_scaffold.mxml
Managed ROOT/src/main/flex/rootunes_scaffold-config.xml
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist/ArtistEvent.as
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist/ArtistView.mxml
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/artist/ArtistForm.mxml
Created SRC_MAIN_JAVA/org/example/rootunes/service/AlbumService_Roo_Service.aj
Managed ROOT/src/main/flex/rootunes_scaffold.mxml
Managed ROOT/src/main/flex/rootunes_scaffold-config.xml
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/album
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/album/AlbumEvent.as
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/album/AlbumView.mxml
Created ROOT/src/main/flex/org/example/rootunes/presentation/album/AlbumForm.mxml
                </programlisting>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="running-flex-addon-project">
            <title>Building and Running a Flex Addon Project</title>
            <para>
                The project configuration provided by the <code>flex setup</code> command prepares the project for both running and building from the command line, via Maven, or running as a Flex 
                and WTP project in SpringSource Tool Suite with the Flash Builder v4 plugin installed.
            </para>
            <sect3 id="building-with-maven">
                <title>Building and Running a Flex Addon Project with Maven</title>
                <para>With the necessary configuration for both the Java and Flex source already set up, building the project is as simple as:</para>
                <programlisting>
mvn install
                </programlisting>
                <para>Similarly, running the project from the command line via the already configured Maven Tomcat plugin is as simple as:</para>
                <programlisting>
mvn tomcat:run              
                </programlisting>
                <para>
                    (Note - The first time you execute these commands with an unpopulated Maven cache, it will take a few minutes to download the necessary dependencies.  Don't worry, after you've done 
                    this once, the commands execute much faster.)
                </para>
                <para>Once server startup is complete, you should be able to access the scaffolded Flex UI at <code>http://localhost:8080/{project_name}/{project_name}_scaffold.html</code>  - for example, 
                in the sample Spring Roo script bundled with the distribution (and in the above examples), we create a project named "rootunes".  Once the server is started, the Flex UI can be accessed at:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/rootunes/rootunes_scaffold.html">http://localhost:8080/rootunes/rootunes_scaffold.html</ulink></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="building-with-sts">
                <title>Importing a Flex Addon Project into SpringSource Tool Suite and Flash Builder</title>
                <para>To generate the necessary Eclipse metadata for the project, from the project root you must execute</para>
                <programlisting>
mvn eclipse:eclipse
                </programlisting>
                <para>Once that is done, the project can be imported into SpringSource Tool Suite and run on a server via WTP.</para>
                <para>  
                    To import the project, select File->Import...->General->Existing Projects into Workspace and navigate to the
                    project's root directory and import the Eclipse project found there.  If you have created the project outside of your Eclipse workspace, you should 
                    check the "Copy projects into workspace" box in the import dialog in order for the generated Flash Builder metadata to work correctly.
                </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sample-script">
            <title>Running the Sample Roo Script</title>
            <para>
                A sample Spring Roo script that generates a complete Flex sample project is included in the Spring BlazeDS Integration distribution.  The script can be found 
                at {project_distribution_root}/samples/rootunes.roo
            </para>
            <para>
                The script can be run using Spring Roo's <code>script</code> command.  Create a new project directory, and then start the Roo shell.  From there, you can point 
                the <code>script</code> command at the location of the <code>rootunes.roo</code> script.  For example, if you've unzipped the distribution in your home directory, 
                the command would be:
            </para>
            <programlisting>
roo> script --file ~/spring-flex-1.5.0.M1/samples/rootunes.roo
            </programlisting>
            <para>
                Once the script has completed, you can build and run the example using the steps described above.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="known-issues">
            <title>Known Issues</title>
            <para>
                As this is just an M1 release, there are a number of known issues and planned functionality yet to be completed.  Some of the more glaring ones are:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The scaffolding does not currently generate form fields for editing ONE_TO_MANY or MANY_TO_MANY relationships, though it does generate the correct
                        field types for the relationship in the ActionScript class, so you are free to add the remaining code for editing such relationships manually.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The generated ActionScript entities currently ignore any superclasses or interfaces that the Java type may declare.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The ActionScript parser we are using is not able to generate property getters and setters, though it should still parse them without error. 
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The ActionScript parser does not give us control over the exact placement of fields in the ActionScript, instead always adding them at the bottom of 
                        the Class declaration.  You are, of course, free to move the field declarations around to your liking without any adverse effects.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The round-trip merging functionality for tags in .mxml artifacts is incomplete.  It currently can add new fields, but not update or remove existing ones.  This 
                        will be remedied through a similar approach as Roo 1.1 uses for .jspx artifacts, only we'll use Flex meta-tags instead of additional tag attributes.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The round-trip updating of <code>script</code> blocks in .mxml files is destructive, meaning it will overwrite changes.  This will be remedied in the future 
                        by applying the same non-destructive ActionScript metadata layer that we use for the .as files.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>    
    </sect1>
</chapter>