<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="samples">
    <title>Building and Running the Spring BlazeDS Integration Samples</title>
    <sect1 id="samples-introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
        	Included in the project distribution is a collection of samples called the Spring BlazeDS Integration Test Drive.  This samples project is set up 
        	to be built with Maven and either run via an embedded Tomcat instance using the Maven Tomcat plugin, or else imported into Eclipse for running via WTP.
        </para>
        <sect2 id="building-with-maven">
        	<title>Maven Setup</title>
        	<para>
	            The sample build requires Maven 2.2.0 or greater.  Because the build compiles several seperate Flex and AIR projects, it can require setting the MAVEN_OPTS 
	            variable for your environment to allocate more memory than the default.  The setting we find works well is:
	        </para>
	        <programlisting><![CDATA[
MAVEN_OPTS="-Xms256m -Xmx512m -XX:PermSize=128m -XX:MaxPermSize=256m"
]]>
	        </programlisting>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="samples-build">
	        <title>Building and Running the Test Drive</title>
	        <para>
	            Once your Maven environment is set up correctly, cd to {project distribution root}/samples/spring-flex-testdrive and execute:
	        </para>
	        <programlisting><![CDATA[
mvn clean install
]]>
	        </programlisting>
	        <para>
	            This will first build all of the individual Flex projects and then finally assemble the 'testdrive' WAR project.  After building successfully, if you'd like to 
	            run the application from the command line with an embedded Tomcat instance, execute:
	        </para>
	        <programlisting><![CDATA[
mvn tomcat:run
]]>
			</programlisting>
			<para>
				Once the application has started successfully, you can access the samples walk-through at <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/testdrive/index.html">http://localhost:8080/testdrive/index.html</ulink>
			</para>
	    </sect2>
	    <sect2 id="blazeds-4-maven">
        	<title>Using BlazeDS 4 with Maven</title>
        	<para>
        		Spring BlazeDS Integration 1.5 requires BlazeDS 4, but as of this writing the BlazeDS 4 artifacts have not yet been published to Maven central.  
        		The artifacts have been published to the Spring External maven repository (as required for the Spring BlazeDS Integration automated builds).  The 
        		Test Drive is already configured to use this repository, but to use BlazeDS 4 in your own Maven projects, add the following repository entry 
        		(either to settings.xml or to your project's pom.xml):
        	</para>
        	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<repository>
    <id>spring-external</id>
    <name>Spring External Repository</name>
    <url>http://maven.springframework.org/external</url>
    <releases>
        <enabled>true</enabled>
	</releases>
    <snapshots>
        <enabled>false</enabled>
    </snapshots>
</repository>
]]>
	        </programlisting>
        </sect2>
	    <sect2 id="pre-built-samples">
	        <title>Download the Pre-packaged Test Drive</title>
	        <para>
	            As a convenience for anyone who is adverse to using Maven and just wants to get the Test Drive up and running quickly in Eclipse, pre-packaged builds 
	            of the Test Drive can be downloaded directly via the following links:
	        </para>
	        <itemizedlist>
			    <listitem>
			        <para><ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring-flex/docs/1.5.x/samples/spring-flex-testdrive-spring3.zip">Spring BlazeDS Integration Test Drive with Spring 3.0</ulink></para>
			    </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
	        <para>
	           Unzip the download and then follow the directions below for importing into Eclipse, substituting the unzipped directory in place of the 
	           {project distribution root}/spring-flex-samples/spring-flex-testdrive path.
	        </para>
	    </sect2>
	    <sect2 id="samples-eclipse">
	        <title>Importing and Running the Test Drive in Eclipse</title>
	        <para>
	            The individual Test Drive projects are pre-configured to be imported in Eclipse and run with WTP.  (There are a number of individual projects, so you may want to consider creating a fresh
	            workspace or at least create a new working set to manage the projects.)  We recommend using the free <ulink url="http://www.springsource.com/products/sts">SpringSource Tool Suite</ulink> to work with the samples so that you can take full 
	            advantage of its extensive Spring support, but any version of Eclipse 3.5+ with WTP should work.  
	        </para>
	        <para>  
	            To import the samples, select File->Import...->General->Existing Projects into Workspace and navigate to the
	            {project distribution root}/spring-flex-samples/spring-flex-testdrive directory and import all of the projects found.
	        </para>
	        <para>
	            There is an individual project for each Flex sample, and one WTP project for the 'testdrive' WAR.  Once the projects have been imported, you can start the web application by selecting the 
	            'testdrive' project, right-clicking and selecting Run As->Run on Server.  The samples have been most thoroughly tested in Tomcat 6.0, but should run in any Servlet 2.4 container that WTP supports.  Once 
	            the application has started successfully, you can access the samples walk-through at <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/testdrive/index.html">http://localhost:8080/testdrive/index.html</ulink> (If running on a server other than 
	            Tomcat, change the port number as needed.)
	        </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>