<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="security">
    <title>Securing BlazeDS Destinations with Spring Security</title>
    <sect1 id="security-introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
        	Spring Security provides an extremely flexible alternative to the container-based security support provided out-of-the-box with 
        	BlazeDS.  Spring BlazeDS Integration provides explicit integration support for incorporating Spring Security smoothly into your 
        	Flex/BlazeDS application.  Spring Security provides a wealth of different configuration options, but rather than go into the many
        	different combinations here, we'll leave most of that to the Spring Security documentation.  
        </para>
        <sect2 id="spring-security-config">
            <title>A simple Spring Security 2 configuration</title>
	        <para>
	        	Here is a simple Spring Security starting configuration for use in conjunction with the explicit integration features 
	        	provided by Spring BlazeDS Integration that should be a solid starting point for securing a typical Flex application:   
	        </para>
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<beans:beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/security"
  xmlns:beans="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans 
                      http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-2.5.xsd
                      http://www.springframework.org/schema/security 
                      http://www.springframework.org/schema/security/spring-security-2.0.4.xsd"> 
    
    <http entry-point-ref="preAuthenticatedEntryPoint" />
    
    <beans:bean id="preAuthenticatedEntryPoint" 
        class="org.springframework.security.ui.preauth.PreAuthenticatedProcessingFilterEntryPoint" />
    
    <authentication-provider>
		<user-service>
	    	<user name="jeremy" password="atlanta" authorities="ROLE_USER, ROLE_ADMIN" />
	      	<user name="keith" password="melbourne" authorities="ROLE_USER" />
		</user-service>
	</authentication-provider>
    
</beans:beans>]]>
		    </programlisting>
			<para>
				With a typical Flex application, this approach is preferred to using Spring Security's auto-config setup.  Auto-config sets up a number of 
				features that typically are not needed with a Flex application.  For instance, auto-config sets up a default <code>intercept-url</code> entry that
				requires authentication for all URL paths within the application.  This does not work well for the needs of a typical BlazeDS setup as it would result in
				the server returning a 403 response code for un-authenticated calls to BlazeDS endpoints which the Flex client does not handle gracefully.  (See <link linkend="secured-endpoint-path">
				Securing BlazeDS Channels by Endpoint URL Path</link> for an alternative to <code>intercept-url</code> that generates proper AMF responses for the Flex client.) 
				It is recommended to start simple as in this example, and add the additional features as needed.  
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="security-filter-config">
		    <title>Enabling the Spring Security filter chain in web.xml</title>
		    <para>
		        For a typical setup with Spring Security, it is critical to remember to enable 
		        the Spring Security filter chain by adding the appropriate entry to web.xml:
		    </para>
		    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<filter> 
    <filter-name>springSecurityFilterChain</filter-name> 
    <filter-class>org.springframework.web.filter.DelegatingFilterProxy</filter-class> 
</filter> 

<filter-mapping> 
    <filter-name>springSecurityFilterChain</filter-name> 
    <url-pattern>/*</url-pattern> 
</filter-mapping> 		    
]]>
            </programlisting>
		</sect2>
        <para>
        	We will assume the above configuration is in place for the remainder of the examples in this chapter.  For additional details on the many options available in 
        	configuring and using Spring Security, please refer to that project's <ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring-security/site/reference.html">documentation</ulink>.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="configuring-security">
    	<title>Configuring the Spring Security Integration</title>
    	<para>
    		Spring Security integration is enabled through the <code>secured</code> child element of the <code>message-broker</code> tag.  The
    		simplest possible configuration would be:
    	</para>
    	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<flex:message-broker>
	<flex:secured />
</flex:message-broker>]]>
    	</programlisting>
    	<para>
    		This enables the basic security features.  A special BlazeDS <code>LoginCommand</code> implementation is automatically installed that
    		enables ChannelSet.login and ChannelSet.logout requests to integrate with Spring Security's Authorization mechanisms.  Additionally, 
    		the special <code>LoginCommand</code> enables Spring Security granted authorities to be referenced in BlazeDS XML security constraints.
    		For example, if we were using a traditional BlazeDS remoting destination defined in remoting-config.xml, we could have something like 
    		the following:  
    	</para>
    	<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<destination id="productService">
    ...
    <security>
        <security-constraint>
            <auth-method>Custom</auth-method>
            <roles>
                <role>ROLE_USER</role>
            </roles>
        </security-constraint>
    </security>
</destination>]]>    	
    	</programlisting>
    	<para>
    		As you can see, we are referencing the "ROLE_USER" authority from our simple Spring Security setup.  The invocation of this remote
    		destination would cause the provided <code>LoginCommand</code> to be invoked to both verify that the user is logged in and to check
    		that they have the appropriate role.  Violation of either will result in an exception being thrown by Spring Security.    
    	</para>
    	<sect2 id="accessing-user-details">
    		<title>Accessing User Details</title>
    		<para>
    			When using the ChannelSet.login API call from the Flex client with Spring Security integration enabled, the resulting ResponseEvent 
    			fired client-side upon successful completion will contain additional information that can be inspected about the current user.  The 
    			name and authorities will be extracted from the Authentication object and added to the body of the response message.  This information, 
    			for example, can then be used to conditionally display different portions of the UI based on the user's identity and granted roles:
    		</para>
    		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
var token:AsyncToken = myChannelSet.login("jeremy","atlanta");
token.addResponder(
	new AsyncResponder(
  		function(event:ResultEvent, token:Object = null):void {
  			if (event.result.authorities.indexOf("ROLE_ADMIN") >= 0) {
  				displayAdminPanel(event.result.name);
  			} else {
  				displayUserPanel(event.result.name);
  			}
  		},
  		function(event:FaultEvent, token:Object = null):void {
  			displayErrorMessage("Login Failed: "+event.fault.faultString);
  		}
  	)
);]]>    	
    		</programlisting>
    	</sect2>
    	<sect2  id="security-exception-translation">
    		<title>Security Exception Translation</title>
	    	<para>
	    		Another feature that is automatically installed when the <code>secured</code> tag is used is automatic exception translation from
	    		any thrown SpringSecurityException to the proper BlazeDS SecurityException.  The exceptions are caught and translated at the proper 
	    		point in the execution chain such that it will result in the proper AMF error message being serialized and sent back to the client.
	    	</para>
	    	<para>  
	    		This is alternative to the normal Spring Security behavior where a filter in the chain catches the exception and sends back a
	    		corresponding HTTP status code.  The problem with sending back HTTP status codes other than 200 is that this causes the Flex client
	    		to throw a generic and rather unhelpful exception, and often the status code can't be determined from the Flex client.  Sending back 
	    		specific AMF error messages instead causes a <code>FaultEvent</code> to be thrown client-side that contains the proper 
	    		security fault code that can then be reasoned on and appropriate action can be taken.  This behavior is equivalent to that of the
	    		out-of-the-box container-based security mechanisms provided with BlazeDS, so the programming model client-side remains the same.
	    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    	<sect2 id="secured-tag-attributes">
    		<title><code>secured</code> Configuration Attributes</title>
	    	<para>
	    		The <code>secured</code> tag has several additional attributes that allow further customization.
	    	</para>  
	    	<para>	
	    		If you are not using Spring Security's
	    		default bean ids for the <code>AuthenticationManager</code> or <code>AccessDecisionManager</code>, you can specify your custom bean references
	    		using the corresponding <code>authentication-manager</code> and <code>access-decision-manager</code> attributes respectively on the <code>secured</code>
	    		tag.   
	    	</para>
	    	<para>
	    		The configuration of the provided <code>LoginCommand</code> can be further controlled via the <code>secured</code> tag.  The <code>invalidate-flex-session</code>
	    		attribute controls whether the current Flex session is invalidated when the <code>logout()</code> method is called on the <code>LoginCommand</code>, and 
	    		defaults to "true" if not specified.  The <code>per-client-authentication</code> attribute turns BlazeDS's per-client authentication mode on when true, and
	    		defaults to "false" if not specified.  Enabling per-client authentication will cause the Security context to no longer be stored in the session between
	    		requests and thus will prevent the use of any Spring Security filters that rely on the Security Context being available in the session, but the authentication 
	    		and authorization integration will otherwise work as expected.  (See the BlazeDS docs for further information on the difference between per-session and per-client 
	    		authentication.)  	    		
	    	</para>
    	</sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="endpoint-security">
    	<title>Configuring Endpoint and Destination Security</title>
    	<para>
    		The Spring Security integration allows flexible control over how you secure your application.  You can secure BlazeDS endpoints in
    		a manner similar to Spring Security's traditional URL security, and you can secure your Spring services using the many existing
    		object security mechanisms of Spring Security just as if you were writing a traditional web application.
    	</para>
    	<sect2 id="secured-channel">
    		<title>Securing Specific BlazeDS Channels</title>
    		<para>
    			You can set security constraints on specific BlazeDS channels using the <code>secured-channel</code> child element of the <code>secured</code> 
    			tag.  For example:  
    		</para>
    		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<flex:message-broker>
	<flex:secured>
		<flex:secured-channel channel="my-amf" access="ROLE_USER" />
	</flex:secured>
</flex:message-broker>]]>
    		</programlisting>
    		<para>
    			This results in any request being routed to the "my-amf" channel to require the user to be logged in and to have the "ROLE_USER" 
    			authority.  If either of those is violated, a <code>FaultEvent</code> will be signaled on the client. 
    		</para>
    	</sect2>
    	<sect2 id="secured-endpoint-path">
    		<title>Securing BlazeDS Channels by Endpoint URL Path</title>
    		<para>
    			You can set security constraints on multiple BlazeDS channels at once using the <code>secured-endpoint-path</code> child element 
    			of the <code>secured</code> tag.  In this case you specify a URL pattern to be secured instead of a specific channel id.  For 
    			example:  
    		</para>
    		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<flex:message-broker>
	<flex:secured>
		<flex:secured-endpoint-path pattern="**/messagebroker/**" access="ROLE_USER" />
	</flex:secured>
</flex:message-broker>]]>
    		</programlisting>
    		<para>
    			This results in any request being routed to any channel whose endpoint URL contains "/messagebroker/" in the path to require the 
    			user to be logged in and to have the "ROLE_USER" authority.  If either of those is violated, a <code>FaultEvent</code> will be 
    			signaled on the client. 
    		</para>
    	</sect2>
    	<sect2 id="securing-destinations">
    		<title>Securing Exported Spring Services</title>
    		<para>
    			Earlier in this chapter you saw an example of using the BlazeDS XML configuration to secure a BlazeDS-managed destination.  Since
    			most of the time you will instead be defining destinations by exporting Spring beans using the <code>remoting-destination</code>tag, an
    			alternate approach to securing destinations is needed.  This is where Spring Security comes in, as all of its existing authorization
    			mechanisms should "just work" when security integration is enabled using the <code>secured</code> tag.   
    		</para>
    		<para>
    			One of the major strengths of Spring Security is the multiple levels of granularity it provides you when securing your Spring services.  You can
    			go from securing your entire service layer in one concise statement:
    		</para>
    		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<global-method-security>
    <protect-pointcut expression="execution(* com.mycompany.*Service.*(..))" access="ROLE_USER"/>
</global-method-security>]]>
    		</programlisting>
    		<para>
    			to controlling access in a more fine-grained manner at the method layer using XML:
    		</para>
    		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<bean id="myService" class="com.mycompany.myapp.MyService">
	<flex:remoting-destination/>
    <security:intercept-methods>
        <security:protect method="set*" access="ROLE_ADMIN" />
        <security:protect method="get*" access="ROLE_ADMIN,ROLE_USER" />
        <security:protect method="doSomething" access="ROLE_USER" />
    </security:intercept-methods>
</bean>]]>
    		</programlisting>
    		<para>
    			to using a combination of XML and annotations:
    		</para>
    		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<security:global-method-security secured-annotations="enabled" jsr250-annotations="enabled"/>
...
<flex:remoting-destination ref="myBankServiceImpl" />
  
]]>
    		</programlisting>
    		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public interface BankService {
  
    @Secured("IS_AUTHENTICATED_ANONYMOUSLY")
    public Account readAccount(Long id);
  
    @Secured("IS_AUTHENTICATED_ANONYMOUSLY")
    public Account[] findAccounts();
  
    @Secured("ROLE_TELLER")
    public Account post(Account account, double amount);
}
]]>
    		</programlisting>
    		<para>
    			to even more fine-grained ACL-based domain object permissions.  For more details on the options available, see the Spring Security
    			documentation.
    		</para>
    	</sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>